This is דף יומי Daf Yomi עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah דף ל"ה.
Daf Lamed Heh.
Let's see if we get the video going. Let's see if I
can
get the angle right.
And
okay, I think we're... I think we're up. Great. This is wonderful.
Okay, I'm just going to get my גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so I was told that yesterday, yesterday you guys left off
at the end of
ל"ד. Lamed Dalet. Today's an exciting day, lots of very practical stuff
talking about non-Jewish cheese, milk, bread, all sorts of good stuff. So
I'm going to very quickly go over a little bit of the
משנה Mishnah that was on the end of כ"ט עמוד ב' Kaf
Tet Amud Bet because our גמרא Gemara is going to be referencing
it a lot and unless you look at the משנה Mishnah it'll
be confusing what we're doing. So you can turn there or you
can just listen to me either way.
Are we going to finish this part here at the end of
thirty-four B?
We will, yeah. I'm planning on coming back, I just this משנה
Mishnah is referenced a lot so I wanted to make sure that
we got to it. Okay, great. So it's the end, the last
maybe third of the משנה, Mishnah, it says אמר רבי יהודה שאל
רבי ישמעאל את רבי יהושע. amar Rabbi Yehuda sha'al Rabbi Yishmael et
Rabbi Yehoshua. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda were having a conversation. It's very
interesting. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, כשהיו
מהלכין בדרך, kshehayu mehalchin baderech, when they were walking, אמר לו מפני
מה אסרו גבינת עובדי כוכבים. amar lo מפני מה אסרו גבינת עובדי
כוכבים mipnei mah asru gevinat ovdei kochavim.
Okay, we know that there's this גזירה gezeirah that there's this law
against eating non-Jewish cheese, why? אמר לו מפני שמעמידין אותה בקיבה של
נבילה, amar lo mipnei shema'amidin otah bekeivah shel neveilah, because,
right, when you make cheese, there's a number of different ways to
make cheese, and one of them is using the stomach gunk from
animals. So they use, non-Jews use the stomach gunk from animals that
have been, you know, haven't been שחט, shechted, have been killed through
a matter that isn't שחיטה, shechitah, so therefore it's a problem. Okay,
but רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael responds, אמר לו והלא קיבת עולת חמורה
מקיבת נבילה, amar lo vehalo keivat olat chamurah mikeivat neveilah, אמרו כהן
שדעתו יפה שורפה חיה. amru kohen sheda'ato yafah sorfah chayyah. But wait
a second, we know
from elsewhere that there's the stomach gunk of an עולה olah sacrifice,
right, is even more stringent than the stomach gunk of a נבילה.
neveilah. And we also know that a כהן שדעתו יפה, kohen sheda'ato
yafah, who's fine with, right, eating this stomach gunk, שורפה חיה, sorfah
chayyah, right, he can just eat it straight up without having any,
without having to do anything to it. Okay, ולא הודו לו, velo
hodu lo, but the rabbis didn't agree with this opinion, אבל אמרו
אין נהנין ולא מועלין. aval amru ein nehenin velo mo'alin. But they
said that it's not really מעילה, me'ilah, right, it's not really a
דאורייתא d'oraita concern. So nevertheless, there's this, this proves, honestly, I'm not
entirely, I don't entirely understand the mechanics of this, but we're proving
that it actually wouldn't be a problem to eat the stomach gunk
of the נבילה. neveilah. Okay, so now אמר לו מפני שמעמידין, amar
lo mipnei shema'amidin, so now רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua gives an alternate
response, right, because he was, his first response was kind of destroyed
by רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So now רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is
giving a second response: Why is it that non-Jewish cheese is kosher?
מפני שמעמידין אותה בקיבת עגלי עבודה כוכבים, mipnei shema'amidin otah bekeivat eglei
avodah kochavim, because non-Jews, they use the stomach gunk from animals that
are used in idol worship. Oh, okay. אמר לו, amar lo, and
now here's the response of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, אם כן למה
לא אסרוה בהנאה. im ken lamah lo asruha bahana'ah.
Well, if that's the case, then it should be אסור assur not
only to use, not only to eat, but also to use, right,
to get any benefit from. Okay, and now והשיאו לדבר אחר, vehisio
ledavar acher, he has no response, he changes the subject. He says
I don't have any response for that, אמר לו ישמעאל היך אתה
קורא כי טובים דודיך מיין או כי טובים דודייך מיין. amar lo
Yishmael heich attah korei ki tovim dodecha miyayin o ki tovim dodaich
miyayin.
He says this פסוק pasuk in שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim, right, seems
completely random,
is it the masculine form, דודיך, dodecha, or is it the feminine
form, דודייך? dodaich?
אמר לו כי טובים דודייך, amar lo ki tovim dodaich, right,
he says it's the feminine form, רש"י Rashi says. אמר לו אין
הדבר כן שהרי חבירו מלמד עליו לריח שמניך טובים, amar lo ein
hadavar ken sheharei chaveiro melamed alav lere'ach shemanecha tovim, right, in the
next part of, of שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim, it says שמניך, shemanecha,
right, it's in the masculine. So therefore this one must also be
in the masculine. Okay, great. And now we're going to go back
to our גמרא Gemara at the very end of ל"ד Lamed Dalet
and you'll see why that was relevant.
Okay, so see where it says... אמר רבי יהודה שאל רבי ישמעאל?
Amar Rabbi Yehuda Sha'al Rabbi Yishmael? Great. So that's where we are.
Yep. אמר רב אחדבוי. Amar Rav Achdavoy. That's an interesting name. אמר
רב Amar Rav המקדש בפרש שור הנסקל מקודשת. Hamikadesh Beperesh Shor Haniskal
mekudeshet. So רב Rav says one who betrothes with פרש's—excrement peresh but
also can be like the gunk in the stomach, right? It can
be like any extraneous thing that isn't part of the body—in an
ox that was stoned because the ox gored someone and so therefore
because it killed someone had to be stoned, it does work if
you betroth someone with that excrement of that ox, okay? בפרש עגלי
עבודה זרה אינה מקודשת. Beperesh eglei avodat kochavim eina mekudeshet. It doesn't
work.
Fine. So now we're going to talk about that, these two, the
difference between these two דינים. dinim. איבעית אימא סברא ואיבעית אימא קרא.
Iba'it ema sevara v'iba'it ema kra. So we can learn the difference
between these two different הלכות halachot in two different ways: one through
logical reasoning, סברא, sevara, and one through קרא, kra, right? Through פסוקים,
pesukim, through verses. איבעית אימא סברא: Iba'it ema sevara: so if we
go the logical way, how are we going to argue this? גבי
עגלי עבודה זרה ניחא ליה בנפחיה.
Gabei eglei
avodat kochavim nichelei benafchei. So when the non-Jews were doing idol worship,
it was actually beneficial for it to have this gunk inside it
because it looked bigger, it looked fatter, right? It was beneficial for
it to look large. אבל גבי שור הנסקל לא ניחא ליה בנפחיה.
Aval gabei Shor Haniskal lo nichelei benafchei. But when it comes to
an ox that was going to be stoned, there's no benefit for
this gunk to be in it, okay? So it should have two
different דינים. dinim. The one with the idol worship should be considered
part of the animal because it's beneficial. איבעית אימא קרא. Iba'it ema
kra. Okay, so now we're going to look at this through פסוקים,
pesukim, through verses. כתיב הכא, Kativ hacha, it's written here: לא ידבק
בידך מאומה מן החרם. Lo tidbak beyadcha me'uma min hacherem.
So nothing shall be stuck to your right hand from the—this is
talking about idol worship, and so it says מאומה, me'uma, it says
anything at all, right? Even the—by implication, even פרש, peresh, even this
excrement stuff. וכתיב התם U'kativ hatam and in reference to the שור
הנסקל, Shor Haniskal, the ox that is being killed: סקול יסקל והשור
ולא יאכל את בשרו—maybe
Sakol yisakel v'hashor lo ye'achel
et besaro יאכל, yachchel, sorry, maybe יאכל yachchel את בשרו—and et besaro
you shall not eat its meat, right? It shall be stoned and
you shall not eat its meat. בשרו אסור: Besaro asur: the fact
that it singles out its meat, הא פרשו מותר. hah pirsho mutar.
Therefore, its excrement is allowed. You could eat that. Okay? So we've
learned through logic and we've learned through verses and now רבא's Rava
going to say: אמר רבא תרוייהו תניא היא. Amar Rava tarveihu teni
hi. So both of these were actually we could learn in our
משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah that we read at the beginning. So
there's an even alternate way of understanding these, or at least it's
implied in the משנה. Mishnah. מדיקאמר ליה: Mi deka'amar lei: our משנה
Mishnah said, if you remember, מפני שמעמידין בקיבת נבילה. mipnei she'ma'amidin bekeivat
neveila.
Okay, so the original response of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was because
you make cheese with the stomach gunk of a נבילה. neveila. וקהדר
ליה: V'kahadar lei: הלא קיבת
עולה חמורה מקיבת נבילה? halo keivat ola chamura m'keivat neveila? And רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael responds back, right? But wait a second, we know
that the stomach gunk from an עולה ola offering is actually more
stringent than that of the stomach gunk of a נבילה. neveila. מכלל,
Miklal, right? This exchange back and forth implies דאיסורי הנאה שרו
פרשיהון—that de'isurei hana'ah sharu pirsheihon something which itself is an איסור הנאה,
issur hana'ah, nevertheless its excrement is allowed, right? Because we're talking about
the
getting benefit from a sacrifice, right? You can't get any benefit from
a sacrifice and yet its stomach gunk is permitted. Okay, that's what
the משנה's Mishnah implying. ומדיקאמר
ליה—so U'mideka'amar lei that was the first half. Now we're going to
do the second half, the second דין. din. מדיקאמר ליה מפני שמעמידין
עוד בקיבת עגלי עבודה זרה. Mi deka'amar lei mipnei she'ma'amidin od bekeivat
eglei avodat kochavim.
So if you remember in the משנה, Mishnah, it then went on
to talk—he gave an alternate response of maybe it's because of we
use the stomach gunk from idol-worshipped animals. וקהדר ליה V'kahadar lei and
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael responds back: אם כן למה לא
אסורה בהנאה? in ken lama lo asura behana'ah? Right? Why isn't it
forbidden in הנאה? hana'ah? מכלל דעבודה זרה אסור
פרשיהו.
Miklal d'avodat
kochavim asur pirsheihu. Right? This implies that an idol-worshipped animal,
right? Its gunk, its excrement is in fact forbidden. Okay, fine. So
now we've gotten to the same answer in three different ways. Now
the גמרא Gemara says: Wait a second, להדר ליה משום דליתא לאיסורא
בעיניה. l'hadar lei mishum de'leita l'isur be'einei. Right?
But wait a second, why couldn't רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua responded back
to the קשיא kashya of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
saying that it's actually not
אסור בהנאה asur behana'ah because the איסור issur is no longer intact,
בעיניה? be'einei? When you have this
cheese... Meaning like the original איסור issur of the, of the idol
worshipped cow or whatever is no longer a part of this cheese,
okay? You can understand that in a couple of different ways. דהמורייס
לרבנן דלא אסרוהו בהנאה, Deha-muryas le-Rabbanan de-lo asruhu be-hana'ah, right, because
דהמורייס deha-muryas hold on, let me remember what's going on here.
Okay, so מורייס muryas is something that you would put a little
bit of like wine or vinegar in often, right? It's like a
type of like a fish brine that you would put wine or
vinegar a tiny bit in it, but nevertheless, רבנן Rabbanan did not
forbid it to get benefit from it because the wine or the
vinegar was no longer intact, right, like I guess it got absorbed
by whatever the fish stuff was, okay. So מאי טעמא לאו משום
דליתיה לאיסורא בעיניה? Mai ta'ama lav mishum de-leiteh le-issura be-eineh?
But when it goes back to this cheese thing, this is now
we're responding why we're saying why רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua couldn't have
responded about the right using the excuse that there's nothing actually intact.
Why? Because אמרי הכא כיון דאוקמי קא מוקים חשיב ליה כמאן דאיתיה
לאיסורא בעיניה, Amri hacha keivan de-okmei ka mokim chashiv lei ke-man de-iteh
le-issura be-eineh,
because of the fact that this gunk is actually the thing that
is standing the cheese, giving form to the cheese, it's as though
it has significance and therefore it's as though it's still there, right,
it's still extant, okay? That's the response. Okay, now we're going to
move on to a slightly different discussion. We're going back to the
משנה Mishnah where it says השיאו לדבר אחר, Hisi'o le-davar acher, right,
he changed the subject. מאי כי טובים דודיך מיין, Mai ki tovim
dodecha mi-yayin, so
what why are we bringing up this פסוק? pasuk? כי אתא רב
דימי, Ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר אמרה כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא.
amar amra Knesset Yisrael lifnei Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu.
So the people of Israel said to God, רבונו של עולם, Ribbono
Shel Olam, God, ערבים עלי דברי דודיך יותר מיינה של תורה. Arevim
alai divrei dodecha yoter mi-yeinah shel Torah. Your the
the words of your beloved ones, hence meaning the sages, are more
beloved than the wine of תורה. Torah. So that's what we're actually
saying when we say this פסוק, pasuk, okay. מאי שנא האי קרא
דשאליה, Mai shna hai kra de-shaleh, right,
why are we singling out this פסוק pasuk to when we right
when he was trying to distract him? When he asked him, why
did we single out this פסוק? pasuk? He could have picked up
any פסוק. pasuk. אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי ואיתימא רבי שמעון בר
אמי, Amar Rebbi Shimon ben Pazi ve-iteima Rebbi Shimon bar Ami, רבי
שמעון בן פזי Rebbi Shimon ben Pazi and maybe רבי שמעון בר
אמי Rebbi Shimon bar Ami said, מרישא דקרא, Me-reisha de-kra, right,
it's not from this part of the פסוק, pasuk, it's rather the
first part of the פסוק pasuk is why he brought it up.
קאמר ליה ישקני מנשיקות פיהו, Ka-amar lei yishakeni mi-neshikot pihu,
he shall kiss me with the kisses of his mouth, okay, so
what's this have to do with anything? אמר ליה ישמעאל אחי חשוק
שפתותיך זו בזו ואל תבהל להשיב. Amar lei Yishmael achi chashok siftotecha
zo be-zo ve-al tivahel le-hashiv. He says ישמעאל, Yishmael, my
brother, clamp your lips together and don't be so quick to respond.
Basically like you know stop talking, stop asking questions. So it's interesting
the חשוק, chashok, I don't know why how he's getting this from
the פסוק pasuk exactly. I guess נשיקה neshikah but חשוק chashok I
don't know where the ח chet is coming in, I can't answer
that, but nevertheless he's using this פסוק pasuk to say you know
stop talking, stop asking so many questions.
Okay, this this this statement here about the the words of the
sages being more pleasant than the wine of the Torah, it's like
it's
like oral Torah being justified over the written Torah, right, that the
sages can extend and
elaborate and interpret.
Right, definitely, definitely.
Yeah, and it's also interesting, we're going to see in another place
in this דף, daf, hopefully we'll get to it, we bring up
שיר השירים Shir Hashirim again. So there's this connection with שיר השירים,
Shir Hashirim, I don't know, it seems like more than just this,
I don't know, I don't exactly understand why these פסוקים psukim have
any relevance but seems like they're there is a connection.
Okay, מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, so what's the reason? אמר עולא ואיתימא
רב שמואל בר אבא. Amar Ulla ve-iteima Rav Shmuel bar Abba. So
why did he change the subject? עולא Ulla says and some say
רב שמואל בר אבא Rav Shmuel bar Abba says, גזירה חדשה היא
ואין מפקפקין בה. Gezeirah chadashah hi ve-ein mefakpekin bah. This is a
new decree
and you don't start asking questions about new decrees. Okay, מה גזירתא,
Ma gezeirta, what was the actual decree? אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rebbi Shimon ben Pazi amar Rebbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, משום ניקור. mishum nikur.
This was because of snake venom, right? So there's this idea that
if you leave things out the snakes are going to come and
they're going to bite it and they're going to leave their poisonous
venom in the thing and then you're going to eat it and
get sick. It's dangerous, okay, which is very strange, yes. And also
I guess it means that non-Jews were not careful when they left
out their cheese is the assumption. And so therefore we're worried about
these snakes coming into the non-Jewish cheese. cheese, and then it's getting
their venom in there and us eating the cheese and it not
being good for
us. Okay? ולימא ליה משום ניקור כדעולא.
v'leimalay mishum
nikur k'de'Ulla.
Oh,
ולימא ליה משום ניקור. v'leimalay mishum nikur. So, if that's the case,
if it's because of this snake venom, then it should have said
because of snake venom, right? Why didn't it give the reason after
all?
כדעולא דאמר עולא. k'de'Ulla de'amar Ulla. So the reason why it didn't
say the reason is because עולא Ulla says כי גזרי גזירתא במערבא.
ki gazri gezeirta b'ma'arava. And עולא Ulla is from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael by the way, that's some background knowledge. כי גזרו גזירתא במערבא,
ki gazru gezeirta b'ma'arava, when they make a new law
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, לא מגלו טעמא עד תריסר ירחי שתא.
lo megalu ta'ama ad treisar yarchei shata. They don't let its reason
be known until twelve months. It's a secret for twelve months. Okay?
This is very interesting. It tells you about
communal politics. דילמא איכא איניש דלא סבירא ליה, dilma ika inish d'lo
sevira leh, because maybe some people will disagree with the reason ואתי
לזלזולי בה, v'atei l'zilzulei bah, right? And they'll say oh, I know
this reason doesn't make any sense, I'm just not going to do
it. So instead they don't tell anyone the reason for a year.
By then everyone's already doing this thing and then okay, then they
can tell people the reason. It's funny.
You know I read in אליהו כי טוב'ס Eliyahu Kitov's Book of
Our Heritage, he discusses the making חנוכה Chanukah into a holiday.
And
he was it's different but it's the same time period. He said
that the חכמים chachamim waited until the next year to see if
it still had the same power or it was only a one-time
significance. And when they saw after a year they made it into
a... this is a little different but it's the same idea of
a twelve-month period to settle down and see. Right, so this is
like the flip side, the flip side of this idea of a
twelve-month period. Right.
So yeah that's interesting, the flip side. In that one it's what
will the people continue and here it's we don't want the people
to right give them the voice. The other one it's we'll listen
to the people's voice, this one we're not going to listen to
the people. But yeah, similar idea. Okay. מגדף בה רבי ירמיה. megadef
bah Rabbi Yirmeya. So רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya says this whole idea
of, right he like curses it, he whatever, he doesn't like the
idea that it's about the snake venom. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, because
if it were about the snake venom, יבשה תשתרי ישנה
תשתרי, yavesha tishtarei yeshana tishtarei, right, then dry cheese should be מותר
mutar or aged cheese should be מותר, mutar, should be allowed to
eat. Why? דאמר רבי חנינא, d'amar Rabbi Chanina, because רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina says when we're talking about this גילוי gilluy thing, this snake
venom, יבש מותר אין מניחין ליבש ישן מותר אין מניחו לישן.
yavesh mutar ein manichin
l'yavesh yashan mutar ein manicho l'yashan. So both old things, not sorry
aged things and dry things, you don't need to worry about the
snake venom because the snake venom doesn't allow them to dry and
doesn't allow them to age. So if you have something that's dried
or aged, you know there couldn't have been snake venom in it,
otherwise it wouldn't have been allowed to get into that state, right?
It's talking about like the chemical whatever, the physical reality of it.
אמר רבי חנינא. amar Rabbi Chanina. Okay, so if that's the case
we need to have a different reason now for this problem with
the cheese, the non-Jewish cheese. אמר רבי חנינא לפי שאי אפשר לה
בלא צחצוחי חלב. amar Rabbi Chanina lefi she'i efshar lah belo tzichtzuchei
chalav. Sorry, tough to say. So because it's not possible
for cheese to be made without there being little bits of milk
left in there. And we're worried that there was, right the milk
that was used to make the cheese was mostly kosher milk but
also had some טרף treif milk in there. And now the טרף
treif milk is still there, and so you're like eating the טרף
treif milk. Because we'll see in a second that yeah, okay, I'll
continue. ושמואל אמר מפני שמעמידין אותה בעור קיבת נבילה. u'Shmuel amar mipnei
she'ma'amidin otah b'or keivat neveila. So remember before we said that there
was multiple ways of making cheese. So one of them is using
the stomach gunk and another one is actually using a piece of
the stomach itself and then dropping the little piece of stomach into
the cheese and that's the thing that like makes it coagulate or
curdle or whatever.
And so שמואל Shmuel says it's the problem is the actual stomach
lining or whatever.
הא קיבה גופא שריא. ha keiva gufa sharya. So if he says
that it's the problem is the stomach itself, so that implies that
the gunk, the gunk itself is allowed. ומי אמר שמואל הכי? u'mi
amar Shmuel hachi? Right, but did שמואל Shmuel really say this? והתנן,
v'hatnan, after all it was
taught, קיבת עובד כוכבים ושל נבילה הרי זו אסורה. keivat oved kochavim
v'shel neveila harei zu asura. So the gunk of non-Jews and of
a non-kosher, non-shechted
animal, this is forbidden, right? So it seems like it's actually not
okay to eat the gunk. Okay, but there's another question that's kind
of strange here. והוינא בה, v'havinan bah, and we discussed about it.
אטו דעובד כוכבים לאו נבילה היא? atu d'oved kochavim lav neveila hi?
Right, so the wording of this previous statement was very strange because
what does it mean the gunk of a non-Jew and of a
נבילה? neveila? Right, how are those two different things?
Right,
אטו דעובד כוכבים לאו נבילה היא? atu d'oved kochavim lav neveila hi?
Aren't they one and the same? אמר שמואל. amar Shmuel. Now we're
going back to שמואל'ס Shmuel's opinion, right, because remember we said
that שמואל Shmuel No, this statement is actually teaching us a one
thing. כוות שחיטת עובד כוכבים נבלה ואסורה. kevat shechitat oved kochavim nevelah
va’asurah. So it’s telling us that the gunk of an animal that’s
shechted by a non-Jew, right? Is a נבלה. nevelah. It’s the same
thing. We’re talking, don’t get over-complicated, we’re talking about the same story
here. And is forbidden. Okay, but now we still have the original
problem, which is שמואל Shmuel seems to be holding two different things
that are contradicting. One that the gunk is okay the first time,
and the second time that the gunk isn’t okay.
לא קשיא. la kashya. This, now there’s not really any difference between
these two opinions. כאן
קודם חזרה כאן לאחר חזרה kan kodem chazra kan leachar chazra ומשנה
לא זזה ממקומה. umishnah lo zazah mimmekomah. So one of them, if
you remember our משנה, mishna, right? Originally רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said the reason was because of the stomach gunk,
and then רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said no, no, that can’t be
it, and then he gave a different
reason. So, שמואל Shmuel the first, well the second opinion we saw,
but the first chronologically, was he says it was because of the
gunk. But then he heard of the משנה mishna of רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua changing his mind and he too changed his mind. That’s
what we’re saying. So there were really just two different opinions chronologically,
but he changed his mind, ומשנה לא זזה ממקומה, umishnah lo zazah
mimmekomah, and we didn’t rewrite the משנה mishna because that’s not what
we do. We don’t want to start rewriting texts. Okay? So it’s
like a historical remnant of what once was. But at the end
of the day, it’s fine. This gunk is fine. Okay. רב מלכיה
משמיה דרב אדא בר אהבה,
Rav Malachya mishmei
deRav Ada bar Ahava,
רב מלכיה Rav Malachya says in the name of רב אדא בר
אהבה, Rav Ada bar Ahava, אמר, amar, this is a different reason.
So right, this whole thing with the cheese is very interesting. Usually
we don’t have like seven different reasons
of forbidding something.
Did you just repeat that one that you said? So in the
end
the gunk, what do we call that stuff? Is that the rennet?
Yeah, it’s permitted.
That’s what we were saying that the כהן Kohen could actually drink
it in that earlier משנה mishna that we just read in 29.
Right. So שמואל. Shmuel.
So שמואל Shmuel says it’s permitted, right? To eat. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That’s what we’re saying שמואל Shmuel says it’s permitted.
Wait, do we allow rennet?
Okay, so oh, so practically this is very interesting when it comes
to cheese, right? There’s the large, large majority
opinion, almost, there’s very, very few people who say otherwise, say that
we don’t allow rennet even if it’s not
made, even if it’s artificial rennet, even if it’s a vegetable rennet.
If it’s made, if a non-Jew puts it in, then it’s not
okay to eat the cheese.
Because of all these concerns going back to the idolatry.
Right, basically because there’s so many concerns, and you can talk to
Rabbi Linzer about this more, but because there’s so many concerns it
seems like it’s like each of these individual concerns aren’t necessarily the
reason, it’s there was a blanket prohibition, right? So that’s what it
seems to be the case.
But here in this point we’re not holding that way at this
moment about the rennet because of שמואל’s Shmuel permitting it.
Well, we could hold, there’s a difference between eating gunk, animal gunk,
right?
That’s rennet, right?
I think that’s what rennet is. That’s animal rennet. I believe so,
right? All these things are rennet, but there’s a difference between eating
animal gunk and eating cheese that has been made by a non-Jew,
right? You could, I don’t actually know how halachically how we hold
about gunk from non-Jewish animals, but nevertheless, even if that’s okay, there’s
a difference between eating cheese that’s made by non-Jews, even if the
thing they made the cheese with was the gunk.
Because, but what if it’s made by a Jew then?
If what’s made by, oh,
so if you’re saying you’d still prohibit it, right?
No, you’re saying if it’s made with a Jew with the gunk.
Yeah, the rennet.
Oh, so that’s a different question.
Oh, okay, that’s what I’m interested in. That, so
I’m not sure about how we hold about the gunk nowadays. I
think it’s, it would be less of a problem, but all of
the cheeses that are made not like Tablet K, right? Tablet K,
they rely on the opinion that there doesn't need to be a
Jew actually be in the premises. Okay. So it’s not about the
gunk, because the gunk nowadays, no, in America almost no one uses
real animal rennet. They all use vegetable, microbial, all of this, this
stuff. So that’s not really the question. The question is all about
Jewish supervision. Okay. Yeah, and there’s one תוספות Tosafot that like says
it’s okay to do
without a non-Jew, Jew there if it’s, if
it’s like microbial, they were talking about vegetable rennet, but that’s the
very much the minority. And that’s why Tablet K, correct. Thank you.
Yeah.
Okay. Right. So,
oh, okay. So אמר, amar, right? רב מלכיה משמיה דרב אדא בר
אהבה, Rav Malachya mishmei deRav Ada bar Ahava, we’re on the second
line, third line, so he gives another reason, right? That we have
all sorts of reasons. מפני שמחליקים פניה בשומן חזיר. mipnei shemachlikim paneha
beshoman chazir. Because
they, the non-Jews they grease the, the sides of the cheese or
whatever with pig
fat. אמר חסדא, amar Chisda, here’s another reason, אמר מפני שמעמידין אותה
בחומץ. amar mipnei shema’amidin otah bechomet. Because you, in order to make
it cheese, they use vinegar to make it cheese, okay, which would
be a problem, right, because vinegar's like wine, and so therefore it
would become prohibited also from benefit. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר, Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak amar, here's even a different reason: מפני שמעמידין אותה
בשרף הערלה. mipnei shema'amidin otah b'saraf ha'orla. Because they, in order to
make it cheese, they use, what's that called? The thing that comes
from sap. Sap from a ערלה orla tree, right? ערלה Orla is
a fruit tree that is, the ערלה orla is if you eat
its fruit in the first three years after planting it. Okay, so
here we're using the sap. And we're going to talk about what
that actually means. כמאן? Ke-man? So who does this opinion hold like?
כי האי תנא, Ki hai tanna, like it holds like this ברייתא.
beraita. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rebbi Eliezer
omer, המעמיד בשרף הערלה אסור מפני שהוא פרי. Hamamid b'saraf ha'orla asur
mipnei shehu peri. Okay, so someone who makes cheese with the sap
from ערלה, orla, right, is forbidden because it is like the fruit.
The sap is like the fruit. We know the fruit's forbidden, and
the sap's like the fruit. אפילו תימא רבי יהושע, Afillu tēma Rebbi
Yehoshua, this could even be the opinion, you don't even have to
say it's רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, it could also be רבי יהושע.
Rebbi Yehoshua. עד כאן לא פליג רבי יהושע עליה דרבי אליעזר, Ad
kan lo palig Rebbi Yehoshua alei de-Rebbi Eliezer, right, the only place
where רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua disagrees with רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer in
this topic, אלא בקטפא דגוזא ella b'kitpa d'goza is talking about when
it's the sap of a branch, right, of the tree. אבל בקטפא
דפירא, Aval b'kitpa d'pēre, but with the sap of the fruit itself,
מודה, modei, he agrees. Right? The sap of a fruit itself is
like the fruit. והיינו דתנן, V'hainu d'tnan, that's like it was taught.
אמר רבי יהושע, Amar Rebbi Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says, שמעתי
בפירוש, shamati be-ferush, I heard explicitly, שהמעמיד בשרף העלין ובשרף העיקרין, she-hamamid
b'saraf ha-alin u-v'saraf ha-ikarin, one who makes cheese with the sap of
the leaves or sap of the roots, מותר, muttar, it's perfectly fine.
בשרף הפגין, B'saraf ha-paggim, but with the sap of, this is when
I first read this I was like what is sap of fruit?
What kind of fruit has sap? But here's
the answer, right, figs. This is talking about
young figs. So it's true, like you know figs if you had
them before they have that sticky stuff on the side. So someone
who's using it with the, who's making cheese with the sap that
comes from the figs itself, אסור, asur, right? So he agrees, it's
forbidden. מפני שהוא פרי, Mipnei shehu peri, because that's just like the
fruit itself. The sap of the fruit. Okay. בין לרב חסדא בין
לרב נחמן בר יצחק, Bein l'Rav Chisda bein l'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak,
תיקשי בהנאה. tikshei b'hana'ah. But wait a second, now we have a
problem with all these, we've just brought all these different reasons, but
with two of them, the one that's talking about the ערלה orla
and the one that's talking about the vinegar, if that's the real
reason, then it should have been the cheese should be not just
forbidden to eat but also forbidden to get benefit from, and we
know that's not the case. So the answer is קשיא. kashya. It's,
I don't know what to tell you. Okay, which tells you all
about, right, like the cheese, there's all this going back and forth
that's really interesting, figuring out the reason. It seems like the reason
was a more blanket one rather than all of these individual reasons.
Okay.
When we say אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, does that just mean commerce
with it, or is there some other way to get הנאה? hana'ah?
Yeah, there are, you could get הנאה hana'ah in other ways. You
could, I mean, there's commerce, right, there's like giving it to someone
as a favor, there's, I don't know, I guess I'm trying to
think. How else could you get benefit from something?
If an animal would eat it, you could feed it to an
animal. Right. But I don't know if
they, yeah, yeah, right, maybe like feed it to your animals, that's
a good example, right, or like use it in some manufacturing process.
That would be like a thing. Like let's say you can use
that ingredient to make X and then you use X, right, that
would be getting benefit from it. With cheese, I don't know, I
can't, I'm not creative enough to think of something at the moment,
you know, but I'm sure there is. Okay. דרש רב נחמן בריה
דרב חסדא. Darash Rav Nachman brei d'Rav Chisda.
So, okay, now we're going back to the שיר השירים Shir HaShirim
topic.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman the son of רב חסדא Rav Chisda said,
מאי דכתיב, mai dikhtiv, right, what is the significance of this פסוק?
pasuk? לריח שמניך טובים, L'rei'ach shmanekha tovim,
and the smell of your oils are good. למה תלמיד חכם דומה?
L'ma talmid chakham domeh?
What is a Torah scholar similar to? Okay, so it's connecting this
פסוק, pasuk, this verse, to a Torah scholar. לצלוחית של פלטין, L'tzlokhit
shel paltin, to a plate of פלטין. paltin. פלטין, Paltin, I don't
know exactly what it is. It's some sort of fragrant, I'm curious,
what does it say in...
Balsam oil. Balsam oil.
Great. So it's some sort of fragrant, very fancy oil. So לצלוחית
של פלטין מגולה, tzlokhit shel paltin megullah, ריחה נודף. rekha nodef.
So when you have this plate of the balsam oil, I guess,
when it's uncovered, right, its smell wafts, it's a very pleasant smell.
מכוסה אין
ריחה נודף.
Mekhusah ein rekha
nodef. If it's covered, its smell isn't allowed to waft, right? Like
so the נמשל nimshal would be right... talking about the תורה *Torah*
scholar, like if he's out in the open teaching תורה *Torah*, then,
right, that's great, then everyone knows about his, I guess, wisdom, but
if he's not, then that wouldn't be the case. ולא עוד אלא
דברים שמכוסים ממנו מתגלים לו *v'lo od ela devarim she'mechusim mimenu mitgalim
lo*. And not only that, but the things that are hidden from
the תורה *Torah* scholar, right,
become uncovered. I guess when he teaches he learns more or something
like that. What does רש"י Rashi *Rashi*? There's a רש"י *Rashi* here
which says מתגלים לו מאליהן בלא טורח כשהוא מלמדן *mitgalim lo me-aleihen
belo torach k'shehu melamdan*. Right.
He doesn't have to work hard to have even more uncovered things,
more like I guess תורה *Torah* be uncovered, it just kind of
happens when he's teaching. Okay, and now there's a fun kind of
wordplay game going on here. ולא עוד אלא *v'lo od ela*, oh
we just read that, שנאמר עלמות אהבוך *she'ne'emar alamot aheivucha*. Okay.
In its original context, this was talking about young women will love
you. קרי ביה *kri bei*, but we don't read עלמות *alamot*, instead
we read עלומות *alumot*, hidden things. The hidden things will love you.
ולא עוד *v'lo od*, now we're going to do it a different
way, אלא שמלאך המות אהבו *ela she'malach hamavet ohavo*. The Angel of
Death loves you. Right, these תורה *Torah* scholars, but in a good
way, not in a like he's going to come, you know.
Oh right, they can't, they can't kill them.
Right, right, while you're learning תורה *Torah*. Exactly. שנאמר עלמות אהבוך *she'ne'emar
alamot aheivucha*. קרי ביה על-מות *kri bei al-mavet*, right?
Don't read young women, read the one who is stationed on death,
right, the person in charge of death will love you. Wow. Okay.
ולא עוד אלא שנוחל שני עולמות *v'lo od ela she'nochel shnei olamot*.
But you inherit two worlds. אחד עולם הזה ואחד עולם הבא *echad
olam hazeh ve'echad olam haba*. But also the תורה *Torah* scholar inherits
two worlds, this world and the next. שנאמר עלמות *she'ne'emar alamot*, right,
קרי ביה עולמות *kri bei olamot*. Not young women, but rather worlds
will inherit you. Okay,
I'm going to take 20 seconds to get some water because I'm
having trouble speaking.
Yeah, while you do, I was just going to say this is
also one of the תהלים *Tehillim* words that are translated,
there's a in my סידור *siddur* it said there are two different
ways of trans whether they separate the words על מות *al mavet*
or עלמות *alamot*. I'm trying to find it. Oh, interesting.
Yeah, yeah. Okay, cool.
I'll be right back.
Let me just get some
water. Okay.
Great. So now we're in the משנה *Mishna*. And this משנה *Mishna*
is going to be talking about more fun stuff, different things other
than cheese, more food, okay? מתניתין *matnitin*. ואלו דברים של עובדי כוכבים
אסורין ואין איסורן איסור הנאה *ve-eilu devarim shel ovdei kochavim asurin ve-ein
isuran issur hana'ah*.
So these are things also foods that have to do with non-Jews,
but they are forbidden, but not forbidden to benefit, right? Forbidden only
to eat. חלב שחלבו עובד כוכבים ואין ישראל רואהו *chalav she-chalavo oved
kochavim ve-ein Yisrael ro'ehu*. So milk that a non-Jew milks from a
cow and there's no Jewish supervision, right? Which this goes into the
רב Rav משה'ס *Rav Moshe's* היתר *heter* of חלב סתם *chalav stam*,
right? רב משה *Rav Moshe* was the first at least big name,
the only one I know, that said that you don't need to
have physical Jewish supervision when it comes to milk, but rather the
government because of like the worry of government control, what's it called,
not control, regulation, that it's as though like there is a Jew
standing there. It's as though we're all there. אנן סהדי *anan sahadei*,
right? Because like the fear of the government coming in and like,
you know, taking away your your certificate? Certification. All right, right. Did
רב משה *Rav Moshe* say this? רב משה *Rav Moshe*, yes, so
he's the right, so that's why definitely in the Modern Orthodox community
and even a lot of some places in the חרדי *Charedi* community,
more in the past, right, people don't need, don't care about חלב
ישראל *chalav Yisrael*. I mean, well they consider that regular milk is
חלב ישראל *chalav Yisrael*. That's what I would say. Not that they
don't care about חלב ישראל *chalav Yisrael*.
Okay. והפת והשמן שלהם *ve'haphat ve'hashemen shelahem*. And the bread and their
oil. רבי Rabbi, ובית דינו התירו השמן *Rebbi u'veit dino hitiru ha-shemen*.
But it used to be that oil, their oil was forbidden, right?
Here we're not talking about ingredients or at least not right, we
might some of these might talk about the worry that there's ingredients
in there, but not actual even right, not the actual ingredients.
So oil used to be forbidden, but רבי Rabbi *Rebbi* and his
court allowed it. והשלקות וכבשים שדרכן לתת לתוכן יין וחומץ *ve'hashlakot u-kevashim
she'darkan latet letochan yayin ve-chometz*. And these kind of like cooked vegetable
or... side dishes, and these kind of כבשים *kvashim* are
things that you use brine, there we go, that's the word, brined,
that you tend to put wine and vinegar into, בטרית טרופה *v'tarit
trufah* and this is a kosher fish but it's mashed up so
much that you won't be able to tell if it's kosher or
if it has also non-kosher fish in it and ציר שאין בה
דגה כלבית שוטטת בו *sir she'ein ba daga kalbit shotetet bo* and
this kind of fish gunk that doesn't have a כלבית *kalbit* fish
floating in it because רש"י *Rashi* says the כלבית *kalbit* fish would
float only among kosher fish gunk. So it's a sign that you
can eat the fish gunk.
Okay, but if there's no כלבית *kalbit* in there then you're in
tough luck. והחילק *v'hachilek* and this fish that's perfectly fine but looks
like non-kosher fish so you can't eat that. וקורט של חילתית *v'kort
shel chiltit*. וקורט של חילתית *v'kort shel chiltit* is really interesting. חילתית
*chiltit* is I think Jastrow says it's like asafoetida or something which,
you know, doesn't really help so much but they actually use it
now in Indian cooking. But it's interesting because this is there
is elsewhere I think also in עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* וקורט של
חילתית *v'kort shel chiltit* comes up and that's where we get the
idea that דברים חריפים *devarim charifim* spicy things have the ability to
awaken tastes.
Because the idea is וקורט של חילתית *v'kort shel chiltit* is very
very spicy and so in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* it says that
like even a taste that was פגום *pagum* that was bad or
older than 24 hours right normally we say is not actually a
problem but if it's like cut with a וקורט של חילתית *v'kort
shel chiltit* or if it's cooked with a וקורט של חילתית *v'kort
shel chiltit* then it awakens it. So that's where we get the
idea where nowadays we apply it to like onions and garlic and
things like that.
ומלח סלקונדית *u'melach salkundit* I have no idea what that is. הרי
אלו אסורין ואין איסורין איסור הנאה *harei elu asurin v'ein isurin issur
hana'ah*. So these are all things that you're forbidden to eat but
you can get benefit from. Okay,
so now let's go to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The גמרא *Gemara*
is going to talk about milk. חלב *chalav* milk, למה ניחוש *l'mai
neichush*, why should we worry about milk? Right? Milk's milk. אם משום
אחלופי *im mishum achlufi* right? If it's because we're worried that they
switched out kosher milk for non-kosher milk. Well why would that be
a problem? טהור חיוור טמא ירוק *tahor chivver tamei yarok*. They look
different right? Kosher milk is white and non-kosher milk is like yellowish
or something. Okay maybe that is the case, I don't actually know
what non-kosher milk looks like. ואם משום עירובי ניקום *v'im mishum eiruvei
neikom* and if it's because you're worried about it being not switched
out but mixed together kosher and non-kosher milk, then you should try
to make cheese out of it. דאמר מר חלב טהור עומד חלב
טמא אינו עומד *d'amar mar chalav tahor omed chalav tamei eino omed*
because we know that kosher milk can be made into cheese and
non-kosher milk can't which apparently is true. That's a thing, it's very
very hard to make cheese out of non-kosher milk from non-kosher animals.
I don't know why that is but something about the enzymes so
on and so forth.
Okay. ואי דקא בעי לגבינה הכי נמי הכא במאי עסקינן דקא בעי
לכמכא *v'i d'ka ba'ei l'gevina hachi nami hacha b'mai askinan d'ka ba'ei
l'chamcha*.
So that would work the test of just making cheese out of
it. So if it makes cheese out of it it'd be fine.
But that makes sense if you're making cheese. But what if you're
not making cheese? Right? What are we dealing with here? We're dealing
with it when we are using it to make כמכא *chamcha* which
is I don't know some sort of dish that uses raw milk
not cheese.
Okay. But still you have an easy way of solving this right
of doing the test case. ונישקול מיניה קלי *v'nishkol minei kallei* right?
You take a little bit. You don't have to use all of
it to make the cheese. You make a little bit וניקום *v'neikom*
and make the cheese out of it. כיון דבטהור נמי איכא נסיובי
דלא קיימא ליכא למיקם עלה דמילתא *keivan d'v'tahor nami ika nisyubei d'lo
kaima leika l'meikam ala d'milsa*. So because no no no but look
there's also kosher milk. It's not that when you make cheese out
of kosher milk it all turns into cheese. There's also נסיובי *nisyubei*
which are whey right? The whey doesn't actually turn into cheese. So
we're worried that if you use that test case right you won't
be able to tell like the non-kosher milk will be like mixed
with the whey and you'll think it's just kosher whey but there's
also non-kosher milk in there so that's not a good test case.
אי בעית אימא *i ba'it eima* or here's another reason why it's
no good. אפילו תימא דקא הוי לגבינה איכא דקאי ביני אטיפי *afilu
teima d'ka havei l'gevina ika d'ka bini atifei* right? So even if
you're using it for right that was a response if you're using
it for milk but here even if you're using it for cheese
there's still a problem right? איכא דקאי ביני אטיפי *ika d'ka bini
atifei* because there's still going to be some milk which is like
in it's like that what's that cheese that has holes in it?
Swiss cheese. Swiss cheese right? It's like Swiss cheese and there's still
some of the milk that's going to be like hidden the non-kosher
milk that could be hidden within the holes of the cheese. Okay
fine. Okay now we're going into our last topic. Which is talking
about bread. Okay.
והפת and the bread. אמר רבי כהנא אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi
Kahana Amar Rabbi Yochanan. So this is also really interesting, right? Because
nowadays we're pretty Ashkenaz, I mean in general we're pretty lenient about
non-kosher bread, right, as long as there's all kosher ingredients of course,
and if it's made from a baker and not like an individual
person. But that's the הלכה Halacha nowadays, but we'll get a sense
of how it developed. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan פת לא
הותרה בבית דינו pat lo hutra beveit dino or בביתי. beveiti.
So he says that bread was never, there was never this allowance
made for bread.
Okay, that's a strange statement. מכלל דאיכא מאן דשרי? miklal de-ika man
deshrei? Right? Why would he even need to say there was no
allowance made? Right? Of course, if you don't say that, of course
there's no allowance made. But no, the fact that he said there's
no allowance made implies that there's someone who says it is okay.
אין, in,
and there is someone who says it's okay. דכי אתא רב דימי
dechi ata Rav Dimi because when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael אמר פעם אחת יצא רבי לשדה. amar pa'am
achat yatza Rabbi lasadeh.
This is a great story, interesting story time. רבי, Rabbi רבי יהודה
הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi went out into the countryside והביא עובד כוכבים
לפניו ve-heivi oved kochavim lefanav and a non-Jew brought before him פת
פורני. pat purnei.
This bread that was made in this big oven. A פורני purnei
רש"י says is like some big oven or something, מאפה סאה. ma'afeh
se'ah. So it's just talking about the size of it. אמר רבי
כמה נאה
פת זו. Amar Rabbi kama na'eh pat zu. Oh, how beautiful is
this bread. מה ראו חכמים לאסרה? Mah ra'u Chachamim le'osrah? Why would
the sages forbid it? Right? Very interesting. מה ראו חכמים Mah ra'u
Chachamim
says the גמרא. The גמרא is astonished. What do you mean?
What do you mean how did the sages forbid? The answer is
משום חתנות, mishum chatnut, right, it's because we're worried that there'd be
relationships that lead into intermarriage, right, because of this bread. אלא מה
ראו חכמים לאסרה בשדה? Ela mah ra'u Chachamim le'osrah basadeh? Right?
But rather, what was רבי Rabbi actually asking? He was saying why
would the sages forbid it in the countryside where there's no worry
of I guess of people coming to marry each other? I don't
know why that might be, maybe you know all the workers there
are men or maybe because I don't know it's not a social
circumstance or whatever the reason might be. כסבורים העם התיר רבי הפת.
Kasvurim ha'am hitir Rabbi hapat. Right? So because of this story, the
people thought that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi allowed non-Jewish bread.
ולא היא, Velo hi, but that's not the case. רבי לא התיר
את הפת. Rabbi lo hitir et hapat. He didn't. רב יוסף ואי
תימא רב שמואל בר יהודה, Rav Yosef ve-iteima Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda,
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef and some say רב שמואל בר יהודה
Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda אמר לא כך היה מעשה. amar lo kach
hayah ma'aseh. No, no, it was a different story. אלא
אמרו פעם אחת, Ela amru pa'am achat, this is what actually happened.
הלך רבי למקום אחד. Halach Rabbi lemakom echad. So he went to
a certain place וראה פת דחוק לתלמידים vera'ah pat dachuk letalmidim and
he saw that it was really that the students had no bread,
right, there was no way for them to get bread. אמר רבי
אין כאן פלטר? Amar Rabbi ein kan palter? So רבי Rabbi said,
what? אין כאן פלטר? Ein kan palter? There's no baker here? There's
no, yeah.
כסבורים העם, Kasvurim ha'am, so people thought לומר פלטר עובד כוכבים. lomar
palter oved kochavim. They thought רבי said what, there's no baker at
all, even a non-Jewish baker? Thus implying that that would be fine.
והוא
לא אמר אלא פלטר ישראל. Vehu lo amar ela palter Yisrael. But
no, when he said פלטר, palter, he meant a פלטר ישראל. palter
Yisrael. He really meant to say, what, there's no Jewish bakery here?
Right, thus implying that it was only Jewish bread that would be
okay.
אמר רבי חלבו Amar Rabbi Chelbo אפילו למאן דאמר פלטר עובד כוכבים,
afilu leman de'amar palter oved kochavim, even the one who thought he
was talking about a non-Jewish baker, לא אמרן אלא דליכא פלטר ישראל.
lo amran ela delika palter Yisrael. Right?
That is only talking about a situation where there is no Jewish
baker. Right? According to that position, you could only eat non-Jewish bread
when there's no Jewish bread.
And there are even now in the הלכה Halacha now there are
people who say that, right, that you can only eat non-Jewish bread
if there's no Jewish bread around. There's others who say that even
if it's like if it's tastier, if you want it more, then
it's fine. But okay, anyways. אבל במקום דאיכא פלטר ישראל לא, Aval
bemakom de-ika palter Yisrael lo, but in a place where there is
a Jewish bakery then you can't eat it. Okay. ורבי יוחנן אמר
Ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar אפילו למאן דאמר פלטר עובד כוכבים, afilu leman de'amar
palter oved kochavim, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even the person who
thought that רבי was only talking about, that was even talking about
a non-Jewish baker, הני מילי בשדה. hani milei basadeh. That's only talking
about in the countryside. אבל בעיר לא, Aval ba'ir lo, but in
the city you couldn't eat from a non-Jewish baker, משום חתנות, mishum
chatnut, because we're still worried about intermarriage.
איבו, Ibo, so now we have this story about איבו, Ibo, who
I think is related to, I can't remember, either רב or רבא,
Rava, I think he's like his uncle or something, I don't remember.
הוה מנקט ואכל פת *hava menaket ve'achel pat*—so he would take and
eat bread, אבה מצרי *abei metzrei*, in the, the limits I guess
between the fields. אמר להו *amar lehu* רבא *Rava*—so רבא *Rava* said
to them, ואי תימא רב נחמן בר יצחק *ve'i teima Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak*, and this is talking about to the people, right? He
said to the people, and some say רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak*, לא תשתעו *lo tishte'u*. Don't
speak—and what's the brackets it says with איבו *Ibu*, don't speak with
איבו *Ibu*. I don't know if not in the brackets, I'm sure
it says something else what the note is. Oh, מיניה *minei*. Whatever,
both everyone agrees we're talking about איבו *Ibu*. Don't talk to איבו
*Ibu* דקאכיל לחמא ארמאי *dek'achil lachma arma'ei*—because he eats non-Jewish bread. So
you shouldn't even speak to him. Okay, and thus we end.
Interesting דף *daf* that has very food—I'm a very food-centric person, so
for me it's a very exciting דף
*daf*.